<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A peaceable plea for union and peace in an expostulatory address to the conformist and non-conformist being an appendix to a late discourse of superstition &amp;c. / by W.S.</title>
            <author>Shelton, William, d. 1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58775</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S202</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184058</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13648965</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13648965</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100965</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58775)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100965)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1046:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A peaceable plea for union and peace in an expostulatory address to the conformist and non-conformist being an appendix to a late discourse of superstition &amp;c. / by W.S.</title>
                  <author>Shelton, William, d. 1699.</author>
                  <author>Shelton, William, d. 1699. A discourse of superstition.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. for J. Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Shelton by NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An appendix to a late discourse of superstition, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100965:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PEACEABLE PLEA FOR <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NION</hi> and <hi>PEACE,</hi> In an Expoſtulatory Addreſs both to the Conformiſt and Non-Conformiſt.</p>
            <p>BEING AN APPENDIX TO A LATE DISCOURSE OF Superſtition, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>There will come a time, when Three words uttered with Charity and Meekneſs, ſhall receive a far more bleſſed reward, than three thouſand Volumes written with diſdainful ſharpneſs of wit. <bibl>
                  <hi>Hooker, Preface to Eccleſiaſtical Polity.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>J. Robinſon</hi> at the <hi>Golden Lyon</hi> in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:100965:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100965:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A PEACEABLE PLEA FOR Union and Peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THERE was not long ſince, publiſhed a ſmall Tract, intituled, <hi>A Diſcourſe of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition,</hi> the deſign of which was, to vindicate the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> from that imputation, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the inoffenſiveneſs of her Rites and Ceremonies; ſo as no ſuſpicion of her being Popiſhly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100965:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> affected, may reaſonably ariſe from her preſent Eſtabliſhments. This was manag'd with reſpect to the Times as they then were, when yet the heats between the Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt and the Non-conformiſt, (who both pretend to an equal Zeal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Popery) were great enough, and a Reconciliation doubtful.</p>
            <p>The ſcene is ſince alter'd. We both have been awaken'd and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm'd by our common Enemy, and it has been generally believed, that no denomination of Proteſtants has reaſon to expect indempnity, or may preſume of ſafety upon the prevalence of the Romiſh inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. And who would not have. thought, that an appearance of ſo great danger would have united the minds of men, would have cool'd their heats and ſoftned their ſpirits, and have molded us to a mutual agreement, and a better
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100965:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> underſtanding of the common in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of the Reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
            <p>But alas! Our common Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers have not begot in us a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe. We do not haſten to a cloſure and accommodation: A great part of men retain the ſame eagerneſs (not to ſay virulence) of ſpirit, as if they had rather periſh aſunder, than be ſaved together. As if they inherited the enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Eteocles</hi> and <hi>Polynices,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd that their very flames ſhould not mix if Perſecution ſhould over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them. Recriminations are bandied to and fro. The <hi>Confor-miſt</hi> is Popiſhly affected and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces towards <hi>Rome,</hi> is a <hi>Socinian</hi> and a <hi>Pelagian,</hi> and any thing that is naught. The <hi>Non-conformiſt</hi> is a <hi>Rebel</hi> and a <hi>Traytor,</hi> ungovernable and unfit for humane ſociety. From the raſhneſs of ſome particular
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100965:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> men, or from well-meant words unhappily diſtorted, a whole par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is concluded, and fierce men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent their Adverſaries with all imaginable diſadvantage.</p>
            <p>And what will now heal us? Will diſputing put us in joint a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? Will writing one againſt another compoſe and ſettle the minds of men? Let men uſe their own diſcretion. I blame not thoſe who vindicate themſelves, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue for the ſatisfaction of others, if in a ſpirit of meekneſs they ſeek to reſtore their Brother, whom they conceive overtaken in an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. But for my own part, when I obſerve how hardly any thing can be ſo well and firmly ſaid, but preſently an Anſwer is prepar'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; how few men are alter'd in their opinions, or ſweetned in their tempers, by what comes from an adverſe party; I much fear the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100965:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> diſputacity of theſe Times is not the moſt likely means to put an end to our preſent controverſies. Yea I do with ſome difficulty ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy my ſelf, that this well-intended ſcript (how far ſoever it is remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from all ſowrneſs and froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) is fit to be expoſed. And were it not in great meaſure ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted by the importunity of a Friend, who having got a ſight of theſe few lines, was earneſt to have them Printed, it ſhould longer be conſidered (though the ſubſtance of it has for ſome good while lain by me) whether probability of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs will warrant its being made publick.</p>
            <p>Sure I am, I mean well to the Peace and Union of all good men, and to the proſperity of this Church. Sure I am, I have no deſign to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitter any mans ſpirit, or make him more angry than he is already. I will
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100965:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> not diſpute the Caſe of Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. I muſt be thought to believe it lawful, (for if I did not think ſo, I would not practiſe it.) Our Worſhip as it is eſtabliſhed by law, is (I think) free from Superſtition. Our Doctrine as expreſſed in our Articles, is not (ſo far as I can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern) Popiſh, nor ſuch to which an honeſt man may not with a good Conſcience ſubſcribe: But inſtead of arguing and diſputing any farther, and ſo perhaps exaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perating and making the breach wider; I will exhort and beſeech in all ſincerity and plainneſs, but as free from paſſion and bitterneſs as I am able to attemper my ſtile.</p>
            <p>And firſt, To you my Reverend Brethren of the Conformable Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy (for I aſſume not the boldneſs to teach my Governours and ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours) I will with your good leave thus addreſs my ſelf: If any thing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100965:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> may be done on our parts to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Diſſenters to our Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with a great zeal to Peace and Unity let it be done.</p>
            <p>When we charge them for ſeparating from us, we declare, That we think they would do wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer and better if they would return and incorporate with us. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der we then with our ſelves: Are there any prudent arts that may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon the gaining of them? There muſt be a great difference put between our complying with them, and that complyance to which we would perſwade them. We boaſt not of our priviledge, as being under the protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the laws, and thereby ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting (without making any ſteps of accommodation towards them) that others ſhould come over to us. But we plead, That becauſe of our obligation to the Laws, we
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100965:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> cannot to the neglect of our duty comply with Diſſenters. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what uſes to be ſaid in matters of liberty and private right, <hi>viz.</hi> That both parties muſt yield ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to each other, in order to an happy cloſure and a laſting peace; this muſt by no means be urged in this caſe. If the N. C<hi rend="sup">ſts</hi> can ſatisfy their Conſciences to come over to us, in obedience to the Law, they will do well. (If they can't, I urge them not to go againſt their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences as will again appear.) But we who have declared our belief of the lawfulneſs of Conformity, and who have undertaken the practice of it, can't fall off to them, unleſs we change our opinion, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our miſtake in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples upon which we have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to practiſed. I ſhall then be peeviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not without ſome ill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign upon my good intentions,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100965:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> miſrepreſented, if any thing I am now ſaying, be thus conſtrued; that we may juggle or falter in matters of Conformity, that we may balk our duty, and be falſe to the obligations we have brought upon our ſelves, that <hi>thus becoming all things to all men we may gain ſome.</hi> For, beſides that this is no proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble courſe to beget in any that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from us, a greater venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of us, or our party and way; ſo will it be doing evil that good may come of it, and will lay a greater ſtumbling block than it will remove.</p>
            <p>But when I ſpeak of yielding and complying as far as we can, in order to the reduction of thoſe of the ſeparation; I mean, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may be done by the regular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our converſations, by the prudence of our correſpondencies, by the obligingneſs of our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100965:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> by our great care that we do not tempt any diſaffected men, to entertain any prejudices againſt our Conformity for our perſon's ſake, as we ſtudy Union and as we love Peace all this become us. Stand we our ground, be we true to our undertakings and practice as we have promiſed; where we are bound up by a Law, as we are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and conſcientious men we muſt obey. But throughout the courſe of our lives, if we can rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably think that any thing we ſay or do, will probably more alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate thoſe who are already preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic'd from joyning with us, with all the circumſpection and wari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs imaginable take we heed to our ſelves; ſo let us live, that we may all with a good Conſcience ſay, It is not my fault that there are ſo many Non-conformiſts.</p>
            <p>By what I now ſay, I do not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100965:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> accuſe my Brethren, but it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly known many do; and though there are many calumnies and ſlanders faſten'd upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable Clergy, in deſign to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace Conformity it ſelf; yet I thought it would look like parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality to give all the caution on the other ſide. Therefore with you my Brethren I have taken ſome li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and they who are friends to peace will take it well. Many of you have written worthily, and with great learning in defence of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but with no great ſucceſs, as to the reducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe of another perſwaſion. Shall we try if ſweetneſs of temper, if integrity of life, if the unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of our manners may have a better effect? Surely the <hi>wrath of man worketh not the Righteouſneſs of God.</hi> We may not think to revile or rail them into that Conformity
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100965:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> into which they have not yet been argued. At the worſt, whatever ſome of them may deſerve to hear; we muſt conſider what is fit for us to ſpeak. Our deportment toward them, may not be with ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſions as may ſignifie any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of our cauſe, then ſhall we by the uſe of the means, diſable our ſelves from obtaining our end, and no methods of prudence will ſo direct us. But if it would be happy for us, as <hi>Brethren to dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in unity;</hi> If the diviſions that are among us, weaken and expoſe us to the deſigns of thoſe who would ruin us both; then is it pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Religious, then is it ſafe and prudent, worthy of men, of Chriſtians, of Proteſtants, of peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Sons of a peaceable Church, to do all that in us lies to gain our Brethren, at leaſt to take thus much care of our ſelves, that no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretions
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100965:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> on our part encreaſe the number of Non-conformiſts.</p>
            <p>And now Secondly, I apply my ſelf to you who differ from us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At your hands, Beloved in our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, (for in him the love we bear to all that would but ſeem to be born of him, it is not the ſea of your gall and bitterneſs that ſhall ever drown) I have no great Cauſe to look for other, than the ſelf ſame portion and lot, which your manner has been hitherto to lay on them that concur not in opinion and ſentence with you.</hi> Theſe are almoſt the firſt words of Mr. <hi>Hookers</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to his <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Polity;</hi> which I therefore uſe, not becauſe I would prejudge and at firſt conclude you full of gall and bitterneſs, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would fain expreſs alike can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and meekneſs towards you. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it as you ſee cauſe, yet give me leave to ſay, I have an unfeigned va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue for the perſons of many of you.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100965:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> It is not (I thank God) the arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance of my mind that tempts me to think I can perſwade better than others, but in the midſt of our warm debates, and arguings, and diſputings, my hearty zeal to the proſperity of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> inclines me to imagine that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe ſtill remains to be done towards a firm and happy Union. Wherefore Men and Brethren ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me to vent my thoughts, and when I have ſpoken ſay your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
            <p>And I will begin boldly with you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, If any of you can with a good Conſcience Conform, for Gods ſake, for the Churches ſake, for Peace ſake ſhew your ſelves men of Conſcience; and if <hi>it be poſſible as much as lyes in you, live peaceably with all men,</hi> and yield obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to your lawful Governours.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100965:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> Laugh not at this ſuppoſition. I judge you not. But you cannot be ignorant, that many thus think of divers of you. Many of your party have bred your Sons to that Conformity which your ſelves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe. A practice which has ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times been thus interpreted. <hi>Not</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Burges</hi> Rejoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. p. 4.</note> 
               <hi>a few of thoſe Miniſters which refuſed Conformity in their own perſons, do qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly ſuffer it in their own Sons: which is Argument ſufficient to prove, that they do not think ſo ill of theſe Ceremonies as their Books ſpeak, ſeeing they love the Salvation of their own Children as they ought.</hi> By ſome other approaches that many of you have ſometimes made to the Lay part of conformity, it has been imagined that if Policy and Humane conſiderations did not keep you at a diſtance, you could come nearer to us. God knows your hearts, not I. I cenſure none of you as Hypocrites in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100965:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> yet give me leave to make the ſuppoſition. Separate not from us, if you can Conform. We will not inquire into the reaſons of your former averſneſs. It will be a glorious piece of ſelf-denyal to recede from your former miſtakes. Your reputation cannot be ſo much hazarded by changing your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, as your Conſcience muſt be diſſatisfied by ſtanding out in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to thoſe Laws, to which yet you can yield obedience. If any of you, between God and your own ſouls believe it lawful; anſwer it if you can to your own thoughts; Why do you break the Laws, and forſake the Church, and maintain a Separation, if with a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence you could come over to us?</p>
            <p n="2">2. If in truth you are not ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied (as in the judgment of Charity it ſeems) if there be any thing in our Communion becauſe of which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100965:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> you decline coming up cloſe to us: yet as you are Chriſtian men, and hope to be ſaved by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of peace, ſuffer me to be thus far earneſt with you. Though you cannot go ſo far as we, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to Eccleſiaſtical Laws, yet out of Religion to God, out of Loyalty to your Prince (whoſe Grace and favour you have often and long felt) as you love Peace and would approve your ſelves conſcientious Men, ſeparate no farther from us than you needs muſt. <hi>Let every ſoul of you be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the higher powers,</hi> as far as you can with a good and a fafe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. And now my Brethren, I beſeech you ſay: Can you not come to Church? Can you not joyn with our Publick Prayers, and can you not hear us Preach? If there be ſome few of you, that think our Prayers ſuperſtitious, yet
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100965:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> this is manifeſt, there are great Numbers of you (both Preachers and Hearers) that have often joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with us: And why can you not do ſo ſtill? Is <hi>neceſſity laid upon you?</hi> Will <hi>woe be to you?</hi> Do you verily. think you ſhould diſpleaſe God, if you ſhould Preach before we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, or after we have done? What if it be a little inconvenient? Would you not have it believed, that you have run many Hazards and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to many inconveniences to keep a good Conſcience; and why may not this be added to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber? Muſt you needs altogether withdraw the people of our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes from us? There was more modeſty among you ſince 1662. and ſome of you cannot yet be perſwaded to keep up your pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Meetings at the ſame hours when the reſt of the Pariſh are at Church. I offer it to your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100965:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> as you are men of peace, and profeſs a deſire to comply with the Laws as far as you can, that you would conſider of this matter. Delight not in going as far as is poſſible from us. If it be not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to come to Church, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you conſider whether it be not unlawful to ſtay away.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If it muſt be thus, let me ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licit you with another queſtion; whatever obligations you that were in employment at or before 1662. may pretend, that <hi>having put your hand to the plough, you cannot look back;</hi> yet can you think it excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable to train up a number of young men, and to prepare them to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed you, and act your part when you ſhall go off the ſtage? Was it not enough that you have been conniv'd at (whatever ſome of you talk of perſecution) and that the Laws have been much remitted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100965:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> your own perſons, but you muſt take care to propagate the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to the next generation? What! is there neceſſity laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you for this too? You have ſpoken much of your numbers that have been laid aſide, but how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them are dead within this eighteen years laſt paſt, and yet you uphold your party, and breed up a race of future Male-contents, that might as honeſtly and credita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly have diverted to other em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments. Yea when any of you dye, the ſurvivors are as buſie in chuſing a ſucceſſor to his Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, as if you thought it a great piece of Religion to keep people from returning to our Church. I muſt confeſs I cannot ſee how theſe are the ways of Peace. If the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> be a true Church, if the way of Salvation be plainly taught in our Pulpits (pardon me if I do
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100965:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> not ſet as high a value upon our Preaching, as ſome of you deſpiſe it) it is beyond my ſhallow capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to know how to pronounce a Bleſſing upon you, under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>peace-makers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. You would fain preſerve the reputation of godly and conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men. You Preach not for cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs or filthy lucre's ſake. If temporal reſpects had ſway'd moſt with you, you would not have loſt your Livings. You Preach prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally out of Charity to the ſouls of men, and the Salvation of many thouſand ſouls are concern'd in the continuance of your ſeparated Meetings. Well! I upbraid you not. I hope you mean well. Yet with the ſame modeſty and meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I ask again, Why do you chuſe to crowd into the City and great Towns? at leaſt why do you not out of your publick banks (for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100965:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſuch it is believed you have) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for thoſe corners of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſome whereof are far from Church, and many have leſs aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duous preaching than is in the City. I preſs not theſe things ſo far, nor with that acrimony, as peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rure ſome would. But I take leave to add a conſideration or two more.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Make no objections againſt Conformity, but ſuch as really diſſatisfie you againſt it. Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply not ſcruples for pomp or num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Make as candid and favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able interpretations of things, as you deſire ſhould be made to you, if your way were eſtabliſhed. Talk not of a Divine Warrant or Command, for every circumſtance of worſhip, when you know, that the <hi>Directory</hi> will as little bear ſuch arguing as the <hi>Liturgy.</hi> When <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> both muſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100965:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> have recourſe to general Rules of Scripture, as well as <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> men. If you cannot bear with things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in your conceit they might be better order'd, there will never be a way of worſhip ſo compleat and pure, but ſome ſcrupulous minds will ſeparate from it, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of greater purity. Why can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not you as well uſe the old Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations as the Singing Pſalms? Why can you not declare your Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and Conſent to uſe that Form of Service, which you could uſe if you were not to Aſſent to it? Whatever is tolerable in your own opinion, bear with it for peace ſake. If you think you could com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pile a better Liturgy, or order the worſhip of God to more edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (which if ever you ſhould have leave to do, you muſt expect that all men will not be of your mind, but exceptions and diſſatisfactions
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100965:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> will ariſe againſt you) yet remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you are not Governours, you are not to give laws in this thing, but to take and ſubmit to them. Wherefore out of reverence to your Governours, take things in the beſt ſenſe. We urge you not, to ſtrain your Conſciences to do that which you are fully perſwaded is a Sin. (That is a calumny which ſome of you would unjuſtly faſten upon us, as if we were Patrons of blind obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and implicit Faith, and taught men to go againſt their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.) But yet neither do you pretend Conſcience where Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is not in the caſe. Deal fairly and <hi>bonâ fide</hi> in all that you urge as cauſes of your ſeparation, and thoſe ſcruples which you can indeed conquer, lay them aſide and diſturb not the peace of the Church with them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Let me ſay one thing more
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100965:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> to you. You are greatly miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, if you think it adds any real advantage to your cauſe, to expoſe our perſons ſo liberally as ſome of you do. For what good Argument is this againſt your Conformity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Incumbent of the next Pariſh is not ſo good a man as he ſhould be? Nay, rather is there more need that ſuch good men as you deſire to be reputed, ſhould get into employment, that the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may not be overrun with bad principles and licentious practices. There is little got by recriminating. You have heard how the excellent Prince <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> would not allow ſuch a kind of Anſwer to the <hi>Century-writer.</hi> If we were really as bad as ſome of your party would repreſent us, yet ſtill theſe are but the faults of particular men: no ſufficient blemiſhes to the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhments of our Church, nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100965:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> reaſons to encourage you in your ſeparation. I ſtudy to avoid diſputing, and therefore I take not upon me to prove, that we are not <hi>Popiſhly affected,</hi> nor <hi>Socinians;</hi> which yet I think I could prove. I think alſo your candor (upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering our Articles and Liturgy) may induce you to have a better opinion of all the Clergy-men in <hi>England,</hi> whom you can think ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and conſcientious, and true to the Subſcriptions they have made, and the Prayers they uſe. As to failures in our manners, tho' I am willing to hope they are not ſo great or many, as the exagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of envious men would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate, yet I wiſh they were few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. I inſiſt not on this plea, that if you were without ſin, you might better throw ſtones at us. Yet this I ſay, Nothing of this nature can be a ſufficient cauſe of your ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:100965:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>But I ask you no more queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nor will I be farther trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to you. What remains ſhall be in common directed to both parties.</p>
            <p>We have on both ſides diſputed, and preached, and printed, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail'd Diviſions, and pleaded for Peace, and acknowledged how de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable Union is: And ſtill <hi>we have looked for Peace but no good comes.</hi> We are not yet of <hi>one heart and one ſoul.</hi> Nor is there any great appearance of our being of one way. Come now: Let us pray for one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. We all pretend to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity. We call Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, and by the merits of the ſame Saviour we hope for that one common Salvation which he has purchaſed; and to enjoy it toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame Heavens. And if it ſhould pleaſe God to ſuffer a foreign Religion to prevail upon
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100965:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> us, no great doubt but we ſhould be all <hi>Gibellins</hi> and in the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon danger. Shall we love and pray one for another. Let us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Church diviſions are very deplorable, and if that be any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to our Prayers, I will offer it in the words of Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If the</hi> Scriptures <hi>were conſcionably</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſtian Concord. <hi>ad finem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>obſerved, men would take</hi> Church di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion <hi>for a greater ſin than</hi> Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>or</hi> Theft. Mutiniers <hi>and</hi> Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>do more infallibly deſtroy an Army, than almoſt any other fault or weakneſs. And therefore all Generals puniſh</hi> Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineers <hi>with death, as well as flat</hi> Traytors. <hi>I confeſs ten or twelve years ago, I wondred oft to find both Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and almoſt all the Voluminous wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Fathers, in every age to be filled with Exclamations againſt</hi> Church dividers. <hi>But now I know a little better the reaſon of it, and how prone even godly zealous Men (eſpecially
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100965:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> young unexperienced Chriſtians) are to it, and of what deſperate conſequence it is. Our union is our ſtrength and beauty. Commonly they that</hi> divide <hi>for the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in any inferior truth or practice, do but deſtroy that Truth and Piety that was there before. I like not him that will cure the Head-ach by cutting the throat. No Maſter, no Law, no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion was ever more merciful, gentle, meek, more for unity, love and concord, than the Maſter, law and profeſſion of Chriſtians. Oh that the Lord would ſpeedily ariſe and ſtir up in all his people in the world, ſo mighty a zeal for Unity and ſanctity, that thoſe Bleſſed Twins might conjunctly flouriſh, which thrive ſo ill when they are divided. And that the true Saints of Chriſt may once taſt that ſweetneſs, which ſuch a bleſſed ſtate of the Church would afford. However the friends of Peace and holineſs ſhall taſt of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True it is, <hi>if we regard iniquity in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100965:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> our hearts God will not hear our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</hi> If we pray for Peace, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour within our own ſouls revenge and ſpite, and ill will: If a ſpirit of contradiction rule in us at the ſame time, when we bewail the Diviſions of the times: If we do not <hi>all that is poſſible, as much as lyes in us,</hi> towards living peaceably, our Prayers will be very idle and ineffectual. But when we have well conſider'd the ſtate of this Church and Nation, when we are throughly reſolved to uſe our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt diligence; then pray we to the God that <hi>makes men to be of one mind in an houſe,</hi> pray we to the <hi>Author of peace and lover of concord</hi> that he would teach us how we may <hi>keep the Unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Oh that we could live to ſee the time <hi>when</hi> as <hi>Brethren we might dwell together in Unity!</hi> Oh
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100965:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> that it were not too much, to hope for ſo much of heaven in this world! How ſhould I rejoyce to diſcern the firſt dawnings of ſo happy a day! Welcome, gladly welcome would be the leaſt appearance of Peace, the very firſt approaches towards Unity. I read indeed that <hi>Abraham againſt hope believed in hope,</hi> but he had the aſſurance of a particular promiſe to make him <hi>ſtrong in the Faith.</hi> But I ſhould flatter my ſelf and dream, if I ſhould promiſe much in this thing. Men abound too much in their one ſenſe, men divide themſelves from the whole, and conſider what would ſingly gratifie themſelves, not what would be beſt for the whole body.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, though I am willing (as I have uſed ſome of the firſt words of Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi>'s Preface, ſo) to conclude with the laſt words of the ſame Preface; yet I am hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100965:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſorry that I cannot uſe them as my own words. That good Man had a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as vaſt as his Learning, and was willing to hope the beſt. But length of time which ſpends ſome humors, has made our diſtempers rather the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable. Yet I will uſe his words, that I may put good men and lovers of Peace, in mind to pray, that the time may once come when we may ſay as he:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our truſt in the Almighty is, that with us Contentions are now at the higheſt flote, and that the day will come (for what cauſe of deſpair is there) when the paſſions of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer enmity being allay'd, we ſhall with ten times redoubled tokens of our unfeigned re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled love, ſhew our ſelves each towards other the ſame, which</hi> Joſeph <hi>and the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of</hi> Joſeph <hi>were at the time of their enterview in</hi> Egypt. <hi>Our comfortable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation and moſt thirſty deſire whereof, what man ſoever among you ſhall any way help to ſatisfie, (as we truly hope, there is no one amongſt you but ſome way or other will) the Bleſſings of the God of Peace, both in this world and in the world to come, be upon him, more than the Stars of the Firmament in number.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100965:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
